A Finding Aid to the John Frederick and Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke Papers, 1887-1965, bulk 1887-1925, in the Archives of American Art aaa.mowbjohn
Archives of American Art
John Frederick and Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke papers
bulk 1887-1925
1887-1965
aaa.mowbjohn
Archives of American Art
0.4 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor John Frederick and art critic Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1887 to 1965, with the bulk of the material dating from 1887 to 1925. The collection consists of scattered biographical material, professional and personal correspondence, writings and notes, business records, printed material, and artwork. Some material relates to the Sunwise Turn Book Shop operated by Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke.
Mowbray-Clarke, John Frederick, 1869-1953
Mowbray-Clarke, Mary Horgan, 1874 or 1875-1962
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1887-1892 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1901-1925, 1965 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1917-circa 1923 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Business Records, 1902-1925 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1919-1925 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1915 (1 folder; Box 1)
Biographical/Historical note
Sculptor John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke (1869-1953) and art critic and bookshop owner Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke (1874-1962) were active in New York City and Rockland County, New York.
John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke was born in Jamaica in 1869 and studied at the Lambeth School of Art in London, England. He later settled in New York City and helped to organize the 1913 Armory Show. As a sculptor, Mowbray-Clarke worked primarly with metals. He married Mary Hogan, art critic and owner of the Sunwise Turn Book Shop. Tth Sunwise Turn Book Shop and the Mowbray-Clarkes' studio, Brocken, were gathering spots fro artists and others to discuss art and politics. John Frederick and Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarked died in 1952 and 1962, respectively.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 1964 to 1968 by William Wilson, whose relationship to the Mowbray-Clarkes is unclear.
Related Archival Materials note
The Harry Ransom Center at The University of Texas at Austin holds the Sunwise Turn Bookshop Records, circa 1897-1958 (bulk 1916-1927).
Scope and Contents note
The papers of sculptor John Frederick and art critic Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke measure 0.4 linear feet and date from 1887 to 1965, with the bulk of the material dating from 1887 to 1925. The collection consists of scattered biographical material, professional and personal correspondence, writings and notes, business records, printed material, and artwork. Some material relates to the Sunwise Turn Book Shop operated by Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke.
Sunwise Turn Book Shop material is found within the correspondence and business records series. A poster and a exhibition catalog for John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke were printed by the book shop.
Sunwise Turn Book Shop.; Art critics; Sculptors
- Biographical Material, 1887-1892; Series 1; 2 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found are scattered materials relating to John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke's education consisting of a letter of acceptance to be an apprentice wiht the Pharmaceutical Society of Great Britain and a copy of the rules for the Lambeth Sleeping Club.
  - Apprenticeship Letter, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rule Book, 1891-1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1901-1925; 1965; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Found is correspondence for John Frederick and Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke, and a letter to an unidentified Dorothy which describes the donation of the papers to the Smithsonian Institution.
  John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke correspondence includes incoming letters and one draft of an outgoing letter. Correspondence relates to his bronze works and commissions. Correspondents include: American Art Annual, American Numismatic Society, Frank Applegate, Karl Anderson, Circle of Friends of the Medallion, Public Education Associatoin, Permanent Blind Relief War Fund, Roman Bronze Works, J. Massey Rhina, William Schickel, and H. M. Shrody.
  Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke correspondence includes personal correspondence and that of the Sunwise Turn Book Shop. In addition to family members, correspondents include: Francis Adams, John Adams, Frank Applegate, A. Hugh Fisher, Frederick A. Stokes Co., Roger Fry, M.T. Garland, Frances Jones, Aiko Kawashima, Riichiro Kawashima, Harry Kelly, Rockwell Kent, J.J. Lankes, Dorothy Lattinop, Orientalia, Walter Pach, Ambrose Patterson, Angelica Patterson, Rudolph Ruzincka, and Marie Sterner. Some signatures are illegable. Letters from Frank Applegate give vivid descriptions of Santa Fe, NM in the 1920s.
  - John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke Correspondence, 1901-1918 (Box 1, Folder 3-11)
  - Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke Correspondence, 1909-1925 (Box 1, Folder 12-26)
  - Envelopes, 1901-1925 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letter to Dorothy, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Writings and Notes, 1917-circa 1923; Series 3; 4 Folders Box 1
  Found are writings by Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke and others including: an article by Mary on Charles Burchfield, a thesis by N.S. Wollf on John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke, and by Frank Applegate and Riichiro Kawashima.
  - "Charles Burchfield Sees America First," by Mary Horgan Mowbray-Clarke, circa 1923 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "John Mowbray-Clarke and His Work," by N.S. Wollf, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Statement on Art, by Riichiro Kawashima, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - On New Mexico, by Frank Applegate, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Business Records, 1902-1925; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Found are personal business records relating to John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke including: two agreements relating to the construction of a monument to Grant and to Theodore Roosevelt; bills and receipts; and price lists. Also found are records from the Sunwise Turn Book Shop which consists of sales receipts and consignment records and price lists.
  - Agreements, 1902-circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Price Lists, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1903-1920 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sunwise Turn Book Shop Material, 1920-1925 (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
- Printed Material, 1919-1925; Series 4; 3 Folders Box 1
  Found is an exhibition catalog and a poster designed by John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke and printed by the Sunwise Turn Book Shop. Also found is an obituary for Professor John Adams.
  - Poster by John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Exhibition Catalog, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Obituary, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Artwork, circa 1915; Series 6; 1 Folders Box 1
  Found is a sketch of coins and other bronze sculptures, likely by John Frederick Mowbray-Clarke.
  - Sketches, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 42)